Guide to the Elena Humphreys Riot Grrrl Collection 1972-1998 (bulk 1991-1996) MSS.394
Fales Library and Special Collections
Elena Humphreys Riot Grrrl Collection
1972-1998
1991-1996
Fales Library and Special Collections
Humphreys, Elena
MSS.394
4.68 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, an object, and two folders in a shared oversized flat box
The Elena Humphreys Riot Grrrl Collection consists of material personally collected by Humphreys while she was involved in the Riot Grrrl movement in the 1990s, as well as material generated by and related to Riot Grrrl NYC's activities including zine-making and distribution, activism, and events.
Arrangement
This collection arrived with no discernible order and the archivist arranged the materials into two series and one oversize series.
Series I: Riot Grrrl New York City
Series II: Zines, Ephemera, and Catalogs
Oversize Series 1: Riot Grrrl New York City
Materials in the oversize series were removed from the regular series due to size and correspond exactly to that series in content and arrangement.
Within each series, materials are arranged alphabetically by title of zine or catalog, or when no title was applicable, by genre. Correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by last name, or by first name when the last name was unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
This collection was donated to the Fales Library by Elena Humphreys in Spring of 2014.
Scope and Content
The Elena Humphreys Riot Grrrl Collection consists of material personally collected by Humphreys while she was involved in the Riot Grrrl movement in the 1990s. These materials include zines, zine catalogs, record catalogs, and ephemera. The collection also contains material generated by and related to Riot Grrrl NYC's activities including zine-making and distribution, activism, and events. These materials include zines, paste-ups for zines, posters, flyers, and other ephemera, correspondence, clippings, mailing lists, and other material.
Biographical Note
Elena Humphreys is a designer living in New York City. In the 1990s, she was heavily involved in the New York punk scene and was an active member of Riot Grrrl New York City.
Riot Grrrl New York City was a group of young women in New York City in the 1990s that were together involved in the broader Riot Grrrl movement. Their involvement was expressed through activism, music, and zine creation and distribution, among other activities.
Fliers (printed matter); Fanzines.; Riot grrrl movement.; Feminist music; Teenage girls.; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); Punk culture -- New York (State) -- New York
- Series I: Riot Grrrl New York City
  Scope and Content
  Series I: Riot Grrrl New York City: This series contains materials related to and produced by Riot Grrl New York City in connection with their work organizing events and creating zines. Materials include zines, flyers, clippings, correspondence, paste-ups used to create zines and flyers, mailing lists, and other materials.
  - Clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence [Anonymous-Beck], 1993-1996, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence [Bernath-Foad], 1992-1994, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence [Gallagher-Lovelady], 1992-1996, Undated
  - Correspondence [McBride-Puzauskas], 1993-1997, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence [Ramos-Stewart], 1993-1994, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence [Suzannac-Yang], 1993-1996, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera-Cards and Stickers, 1989, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera-Flyers and Posters, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mailing Lists, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Paste-Ups, 1994, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Riot Grrrl NYC, #1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Riot Grrrl NYC was written and compiled by the Riot Grrrl group in New York, NY.
    Issue #1 of Riot Grrrl NYC is titled Rape and Ritual, and is focused on organized religion as a tool of social control, as well as the links between religion and sexual assault. The issue contains a piece called "Girl gangs must rule all towns" by Kathleen Hanna, as well as personal stories of sexual assault. There are numerous poems, often written by Jill Wienbrock, that predominantly deal with themes of sexual and physical assault. The issue also includes reviews of records.
    Issue #2 of Riot Grrrl NYC begins with an editorial on refusing to soften the tone of the zine to accommodate male readers. The issue contains poetry and prose, often on the theme of sexual assault, and includes excerpts from the book Moons by Jane Hohenberger. There are reviews of shows by Babes in Toyland, Huasipungo, and Lunachicks, as well as a Bikini Kill show at Wesleyan University and printed lyrics of Bikini Kill songs. The zine also features a bell hooks clipping, an advert for WHAM (Women's Health Action and Mobilization), and a report back from the DC March for Women's Lives on April 5th 1992.
    Issue #3 of Riot Grrrl NYC is dated October 1992 and begins by announcing that Riot Grrrl NYC meetings will be held at Reconstruction Records on East 6th Street every Sunday. There is also an advert from Flytrap Records, seeking all-female bands. The issue addresses the intersections of performance and politics in an article on burlesque and The Bowery Girls, and also refers to homophobic attacks taking place in the state of Oregon. There is poetry dispersed throughout the issue.
    Issue #4 of Riot Grrrl NYC is dated January 1993 and is dedicated to the memory of Audre Lorde, who died in November 1992. There are further references to current events through newspaper clippings detailing war rapes of Bosnian and Croatian women during the Yugolsav Wars. The issue also contains a satirical gossip page, a recipe page, and a letter from a woman trying to encourage people to smoke less during riot grrrl meetings.
    Issue #5 of Riot Grrrl NYC is dated March 1993. Quotes from various girls about what riot grrrl means are dispersed throughout this zine. Media critiques include examples of the backlash against the movement in the press, as well as critiques of the mainstream girls' magazine Sassy. Calls for participation include projects on sexual abuse and radical activism. Personal writings focus on relationships with mothers, in addition to the destructive effects of drug use to friendship. The zine features reviews of books and local art by and about women and women's issues. An audio compilation of spoken word to support the pro-choice movement is described. The zine concludes with an extended interview with Jennifer Blowdryer and an excerpt from her book Wrong Wrong Wrong.
    Issue #6 of Riot Grrrl NYC is dated April 1993. The issue begins with ecofeminist poetry and prose from the anthology Sisters of the Earth by Lorraine Anderson. There is also additional poetry and prose on themes of sexual assault, hetrosexual relationships, and lesbianism dispersed throughout the issue. The issue contains a selection of articles dealing with pornography, alternative pornography, and Andrea Dworkin's views on pornography. There is also an article on street harassment that focuses on a series of cards a woman made to hand out to men who harass women on the street. Music components include a review of the 1991 split LP Bikini Kill and Huggy Bear.
  - Scrapbook (Removed from Binder), 1993, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Zines, Ephemera, and Catalogs
  Series II consists of zines, ephemera, and catalogs collected by Elena Humphreys related to the Riot Grrrl Movement and punk culture in general.
  - Ablaze, #10, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Action Girl, #2, 3, 4, 6, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Action Teen, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Adventure Playground, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Alice the Camel, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Alternative Tentacles Records, 1990, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annoyance, #2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Artaud-Mania, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Auto Show, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bikini Kill: A Color and Activity Book, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Blowin Chunxxx, #5, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Can You Hear Me?, #1, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Candy-Ass Records, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Caught in Flux, #4, 5, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Cheese Log, #8, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chickfactor, #10, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chumpire, # 25, 32, 34, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chop Suey Spex, #1, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Crash Position, #3, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Corner Brokerage, #10, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cupsize, #3, 4, 5, 1995,1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Damaged Goods, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dear Kevin, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Dischord Records Catalog, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Double Agent, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - [Ephemera-Cards, Stickers, Memorabilia], Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - [Ephemera-Flyers, Mailers], 1994, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Exercises in Mundanity, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Facts About Dieting and Eating Disorders, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fake Magazine, #0, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fleabites, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gay White Trash, #11, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Girlfriend, #2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Girl Germs, #3, 4, 1991- 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8a)
    Girl Germs was a zine written and compiled by Molly Neuman and Allison Wolfe of the band Bratmobile. Issue #3 is grouped into five chapters entitled: The Rapture, The Tribulation, In The Wilderness, The Great Tribulation, and The House of Temptation. It includes short stories on themes of sexual and physical abuse, as well as a story by Karen Catchpole about "The Many Myths of Masturbation." The issue also includes an interview with Rebecca Odes of the band Love Child, a piece on the films of Sadie Benning, and an article about the band Circus Lupus. There are also numerous letters from female readers of Girl Germs as well as a short history of Girl Germs written by Neuman and Wolfe.
    Issue #4 of Girl Germs contains a selection of short stories, poems, letters, and interviews, on the themes of, most prominently, music and female sexulaity. This includes an interview conducted by Allison Wolfe with the band 7 Year Bitch, a piece by Wolfe called "What is Punk?", a poem called "Boys Are Doing the Gogo Now" by Cunts With Attitude, and a piece on being a teenage lesbian. There is also a letter reviewing Girls Night at the International Pop Underground Convention held in Olympia, Washington on August 20th 1991.
  - Greedy Bastard, #1, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gregjaw, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Guerita, #1, April 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Gunk, #4, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Gunk was a zine written and compiled by Ramdasha Bikceem. Issue #4 has "Have You Seen Me?" and "What Degenerate Created this Abortion?" on the front cover. The issue primarily addresses themes of music, race, riot grrrl, skateboarding and fanzine culture. Bikceeem discusses people of color in the punk scene, and writes a review of the 1992 Riot Grrrl Convention in Washington D.C. where her band, also called Gunk, played and in which she addresses the lack of diversity among attendees. The issue also contains a letter from Selwyn Harris who created the zine Happyland, an interview with Olga Snodgrass of the fanzine Tales of Blarge, and a list of other zines headed by an Ian Svenonius quote, "I'm sure the CIA keeps files on every fanzine kid in America." Bikceem also reprints a flyer from Riot Grrrl Press.
  - Harriet Records, Fall 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Home, #2, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Incite, #30, July 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Indier Than Thou, #1, Winter 1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - It's, It's Weird, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Jelly Slide, #4, 5, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kiki Zine, #1, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Kill Rock Stars, 1993, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kill Your Parents, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - K [Records] Catalogs, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Leeds & Bradford Riot Grrrl, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Leeds and Bradford Riot Grrrl was a zine written and compiled by the riot grrrl group in Leeds, England and Bradford, England. This is a compilation of the first three issues as well as a section entitled "Our Herstory" that provides a history of the Leeds and Bradford Riot Grrrl group. The zine primarily addresses themes of music, misogyny in music, and riot grrrl as a means to confront this misogyny. The zine includes information on Riot Grrrl Press in the United States, and a guide on how to make records, tapes, and CDs. There is also a piece entitled "What NME did not print." This was written for the journalist Liz Evans to use in an article in NME magazine; Evans, however, did not include the piece and her article on Leeds and Bradford Riot Grrrl - as mentioned in "Our Herstory" - was factually inaccurate.
  - Letra de Sangre, Undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Let's Have a Bakesale!", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Lost I.D.: Feminist Women of Color Shout, Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Mad Planet, #2, 3, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Maximum RocknRoll, #79.5, Undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Meat Offerings, #39, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Mudflap, #5, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Mudflower Compilation, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Murder Can Be Fun, #15, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - The Murder Can Be Fun 1994 Datebook (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - My Need to Speak on the Subject of Jackson Pollock, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Nation of Ulysses, #3, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - New York What?, #1, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Nine Months After Diagnosis, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - No Choice XX: Oakland Straight Edge, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Not Always the News, #2, 3, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Not Your Bitch, #1, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Opposite, Part One, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Outpunk, #3, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pilgrimage, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Plotz, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Plotz Lite, #1, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Plume, #4, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - PNMV, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Power Toot, #2, 3, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Princess Magazine, #1, Spring 1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Radio On, Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Radio Riot, #1-36, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Riot Grrrl [DC], July 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Riot Grrrl [DC] was a free, weekly mini-zine produced and distributed in Washington D.C. This issue is from July 1991. The mini-zine begins with a weekly section by Allison Wolfe of the band Bratmobile entitled "Scams, Riots, And Broken Rules To Live By" - this issue's installment includes how to slash tires on cars and how to send mail for free. The zine focuses predominantly on riot grrrl music and the riot grrrl movement. There are listing for Bratmobile shows and information on the band Bikini Kill. There is also a list of other zines, including Bikini Kill, Germs, Jigsaw, and Chainsaw.
  - Riot Grrrl New England, #1, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Riot Grrrl New England was written and compiled by two women, Allie and Margaret. There are references to zine culture and reviews of other zines including, Fantastic Fanzine, Bikini Kill #2, and Riot Grrrl DC #6. Prose includes "Isn't This Romantic," a story about an abusive partner, and an excerpt from the book Women Who Kill by Ann Jones. There is also a page listing herbal remedies for women's health problems.
  - Riot Grrrls Outer Space Cool Stuff Catalog, #1, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Riot Grrrl Press Catalog, Early 1994 [DC] (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Riot Grrrl Richmond, Virginia, #1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Issue #1 of Riot Grrrl Richmond, Virginia is headed Girl Unrest on the front page. The issue begins with statement of purpose for the Riot Grrrl Richmond group as well as an advert providing the details of their meetings. Writings continue on the theme of riot grrrl and include "Why I Am A Riot Grrrl" and "Riot Grrrl And My Self Revolution". Other writings deal with misogyny, including a definition of sexual harassment and how to respond to it, as well as poetry and first person prose on topics of rape, feminism, and abortion. The back cover of the zine features a diagram of the clitoris.
  - Riot Grrrl [Valley], 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Riot Grrrl Valley was produced in Pioneer Valley in Massachusetts. The contributors were students at the 5 colleges in the region: Amherst College, Hampshire College, Mount Holyoke College, Smith College, and University of Massachusetts Amherst. Issue #2 is dated March 1992. The zine contains personal writings and poetry on topics of manipulation and sexual assault. There are additional personal writings on street harassment and abusive friendships. Jen from the band Flowerthief writes a piece giving advice to female-led bands on how to respond to misogyny from musicians and music stores. There is also a piece that provides information on yeast infections. The zine ends by listing definitions of the terms Matriarchy, Patriarchy, and Anarchy. Cartoons are dispersed throughout the issue.
    Issue #3 of Riot Grrrl Valley begins with a piece called "My Babies," which discusses childcare and ends by calling for "Childcare Not Warfare." Other writings focus on women being told to smile, and an advice piece by Jessica on "10 Ways To Sleep Like A Baby." There is a call out from Jenna at Hampshire College looking for women and men to contribute to a cassette and zine compilation on topics of, but not limited to, sexism and gender oppression. The zine contains an advert for an upcoming show featuring the bands Bikini Kill, Flowerthief, Bad Dreamhouse, and Tsunami. The zine ends with a call for submissions.
  - Satan Wears a Bra, #3, April, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Self Help, It's About Women and Our Empowerment, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Shrive/Fleabites, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Simple Machines, March/April, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Slug & Lettuce, #1, 19, 20, 24, 25, 28, 33, 34, 35, 38, 1991-1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Sloppy, Undated, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Sonic Death, #4, 5, 6, 7, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - A Special Book for Boys and Girls, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Splashdown, #4, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Spork, Summer, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - The State is Great, #5, Undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Stoneface, #1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Tail Bone Raw, Undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Teen Beat Catalog, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Tenacious D's Voyage Through His Black & White, 2-Dimensional Life, Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - This Was Your Life, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - [Ulysses Speaks compilation], Undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    A compilation zine of excerpts from Ulysses Speaks zine and other Nation of Ulysses ephemera.
  - Utopya, #1, February, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Vagina, Undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Violet, #1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - What? Zines Catalog, #1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Why Music Sucks, #10, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Women's Underground Music Directory for NYC, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Zugang Presents: Dead Molly, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Series III: Objects
  - Suitcase, undated (Item 394.2.0001)
    Vintage suitcase circa 1940s, in which Humphreys stored her archive of riot grrrl material. Suitcase is covered in riot grrrl stickers, band stickers, and other political stickers.
- Oversize Series I: Riot Grrrl New York City
  Oversize Series I: Riot Grrrl New York City: This series corresponds in scope and content to Series I. These materials were separated due to size.
  - Clippings, 1992 (Box Shared Fales 116, Folder 13)
  - Ephemera-Flyers and Posters, Undated, 1993 (Box Shared Fales 116, Folder 14)